Hey guys, in this video, we're gonna talk
about one last feature of Tableau that you need to know about to use
Tableau to it's full potential. That feature is called parameters. Parameters are basically placeholders for
really anything you can think about. It could be a placeholder for
a string, or a number, or a date. What makes them important is that they
are interactive, so they are there so that the user, which can be you or
someone looking at your data or your dashboards can change
them very quickly, either by clicking on a drop down or by writing
something in or by clicking on them. What makes them different than
filters is that their global. So if you can change a perimeter in one
worksheet, it will change in all the other worksheets as well, so that can make them
very useful for making story points. The other thing that is nice about them is
that you can use them in calculations, so that makes calculations even more powerful
and dynamic than we thought before. In this video, we are going to
use a parameter as an alternative to putting the break calculation we
made last time on the filter shelf. So we'll use the parameter to find how
many states we're gonna look at in every single job title subgroup. To do that, I want you to go to
your Tableau worksheet again and go to where we were before. Our strategy for making the parameter and using it to define how many states we're
gonna see, it's gonna be two fold. First we're gonna make the parameter, and
then we're going to make a calculation that compares the rank in each one
of these items to the parameter, then we'll put that calculation
on the filter shelf and that will provide the same type of
functionality that we see here. So to make parameter, just like
anything else, you can either right click here in your variable pane or
drop down to the analysis here. So let's right click here and
go to create parameter. Let's call this parameter, Top X. It's dynamic, so we're going to use X to
represent the fact that it's dynamic. Data type, you can choose
a bunch of different options. We'll choose integer because we're going
to just use integers as our cut-offs. And let's make the current value five for
right now. Display format,
you can choose a lot of different options. We'll choose automatic and we will allow
all values for right now, so say okay. And you can see that our top
X parameter is down here, and you can, just like anything else, treat it
just like any other measure or dimension. So now we need to make the calculation
that compares the Top X to the rank that we made when
we made this variable here. Okay now let's make our calculation
that will compare our rank to our new parameter. Right click, make create calculated field, and let's call this in Top X. And we're going to compare our rank, which
we made up here as our rank calculation. We're gonna ask is it
less than our parameter? And one thing to notice here,
is that our parameter is in purple, so just like we were talking
about how certain types of calculations are in blue and
the titles of, of individual variables are in orange,
parameters are always in purple. The other thing that you should know is
that this calculation is going to create a logical calculation. So whenever this is true, it will output
the word true, whenever it's false, it will output the word false. So when we filter,
we will filter on either true or false. So go ahead and press okay. And you can see over here our,
our calculation. And if you look at the little icon next to
it, you will see an equal sign and a T|F. So that let's you know that it
is a true false calculation. Okay, so now the next thing we need to
do is we need to be able to interact with our parameters. So much like the filters, you can right
click and go to show parameter control. Now you can see over here where
there's a box where you can type in exactly what value you want for
the parameter. Let's put our calculation over here
in filter and let's press True. So we're only going to look at states that have a rank that is less
than the parameter. Okay, so if we take our other Our other calculation off, you see we
don't quite see what we want to see. Why is that? Let's take our parameter
back to the detail shelf, and let's edit table calculation. We forgot that we have to tell it how to
compute so we're going to compute and in advance we're going to
skip those other options. We're going to put work
state in addressing, we're going to use automatic, say okay. The results are completed
along the work state for each job in the job title sub group. You can see that this is our formula. Hit okay. Press True. We see what we expect to see
with one exception, perhaps. And that's that our parameter says five,
but we only see four different states
in each one of these subcategories. Why is that? That's because our calculations said
less than five not less than or equal to five, so we can go back and change that calculation and
Top X, let's go back to edit. Let's say less than or equal to. Now, when we put this
in the detail shelf and we edit the table calculation so
that it addresses work state, when we put it on the filter. It will show five states for
every job title subgroup, and we now can change this very quickly,
so if we put it to seven we'll give us the top seven states
in each job title subgroup, and if we change it to three,
tt will change it to the top three. So this can be very useful when you
want to change the visualization across multiple different worksheets. Great job. In the last bunch of lessons,
you learned how to make all kinds of calculations including some
that are very complex and hard for many people to do and
you've learned how to use parameters. You now are ready to make very dynamic and
very interesting and powerful dashboards. That's what we'll do in the next lesson.